Simon Kapitza

Quantitative & Applied Ecology Group (QAEco)
The University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, 3010

simon.kapitza.research@gmail.com

♥ @simonecology Website GitHub

I am an interdisciplinary quantitative ecologist researching interactions between socio-economic and biophysical drivers of biodiversity change. My key strength is in quantifying links between economic and ecological systems to capture and predict human impacts on ecosystems, biodiversity and species.

Skills

Leadership	Coordination of interdisciplinary, international research; independent planning of research visits and collaborations; suggesting, planning and co-hosting conference symposium.
Data Analysis	Proficient R user with experience in knitr, sweave, and RMarkdown, as well as integration of basic C++ via the RCpp package. Particularly experienced with very large spatial data sets and parallel processing (MaxEnt, Regression Trees, Linear Mixed Models). GitHub for version control. Intermediate experience with Python, SQL, ArcGIS, QGIS.
Languages	German ●●● English ●●● Spanish ●●○ French ●○○

Education

2017 - present	PhD - Science University of Melbourne Supervisors: Prof Brendan Wintle, Dr Nick Golding
	Project: Global integrated assessment of biophysical and socioeconomic drivers of biodiversity
	change
2013 - 2016	MSc - Environmental Sciences (High Distinction), Albert-Ludwigs-Universitaet Freiburg
	Supervisors: Prof Carsten Dormann, Prof Brendan Wintle
	Project: Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Australian Great Desert Skinks under a changing fire regime (in collaboration with QAEco)
2009 - 2013	BSc Hon - Environmental Science and Politics University of Stirling
	Supervisor: Prof Daisy Dent
	Project: Rural Livelihoods in Changing Contexts: Causes and Impacts of Deforestation in Ta
	Veaeng District, Cambodia
2011 - 2012	Study Abroad University of Sydney

Scholarly visits

2020	Conservation Biogeography Lab, Humboldt University Berlin, Collaborator: Prof Tobias
	Kuemmerle (March 2020 - present)
2019 - 2020	Zurell lab, Humboldt University Berlin, Collaborator: Dr Damaris Zurell (June 2019 - March
	2020)
2019	Centre for Biodiversity and Environment Research, University College London, Collaborator:
	Dr Tim Newbold (June 2019)

Professional experience

2018-2019	Research Assistant, The Spatial Solutions Fire Ecology Project (University of Melbourne)
2016 - present	Research Assistant, Quantifying Impacts of Trade on Biodiversity (University of Melbourne)
2014 - 2015	Research Assistant, Climate Data Analysis and Modelling (Fraunhofer ISE)
2012 - 2013	Social Media Manager, Creative Stirling
2012	Project Management Intern, German Embassy Colombo
2011	Field Intern, German Agro Action e.V. Cambodia
2008 - 2009	Workshop coordinator, Youth Educational Institute Jugendbildungsstaette Juist

Awards and scholarships

2019	David H Ashton Scholarship, University of Melbourne (AUD 2900)
2018	Wiley Award for Best Poster, International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews
	Science Abroad Travelling Scholarship, University of Melbourne (AUD 1500)
	Financial Support for Research or Conference Travel, University of Melbourne (AUD 2000)
	Drummond Travel Award (AUD 1500)
2017	Australian Research Council Discovery top-up grant (AUD 21,000)
	Melbourne International Research Scholarship (AUD 120,000)
2015	DAAD PROMOS Scholarship grant (2300 EUR)

Publications

Kapitza, S., Ha, P. V., Golding, N., Kompas, T, Cadenhead, N. C. R., Bal, P., Wintle, B.A., Assessing biophysical and socio-economic impacts of climate change on biodiversity (under review, Preprint: arXiv:2002.02721v1)

Kapitza, S., Golding, N., Improved spatially-explicit land-use change modelling to predict future land use and biodiversity outcomes (in prep)

Presentations

2019 The economy, climate change and biodivers	2019	The economy,	climate	change	and	biodiversit	V
--	------	--------------	---------	--------	-----	-------------	---

Applied Geoinformation Science Colloquium, Humboldt University of Berlin

Biogeography Colloquium, Humboldt University of Berlin

Centre for Biodiversity and Environmental Research, University College London

2018 Integrating drivers of change: an assessment of bio-physical and socio-economic climate

change impacts on species habitat

Australian Ecological Society Conference, Brisbane British Ecological Society Annual Meeting, Birmingham

Accounting for socio-economic impacts in biodiversity modelling

British Ecological Society Quantitative Ecology Spatial Interest Group conference, St. Andrews

Assessing direct and indirect impacts of climate change on bird habitat

Poster, International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews

Indirect impacts of climate change on future bird habitat in Vietnam and Australia

PhD confirmation seminar, School of BioSciences, University of Melbourne

Comparing the biophysical and economic impacts of climate change on biodiversity

Guest seminar, Helmholtz Institute for Zoology and Wildlife Research, Berlin

2017 Accounting for socioeconomic drivers of biodiversity change: A novel integrated assess-

ment framework

Seminar, Quantitative & Applied Ecology Group, University of Melbourne

Workshops

2019	CBRI Grand Challenges

University of Melbourne Computational Biology Research Initiative

2018 Spatial Point Pattern Analysis

Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence for Mathematical and Statistical Frontiers

Combining Different Data Types In a Single Model International Statistical Ecology Conference 2018

Academic activities

2020	Global Ecology and Biogeography Peer reviewer
2019	British Ecological Society Annual Meeting Symposium Organiser and Chair

2018 - present British Ecological Society Quantitative Ecology Group Committee Member

2017 - 2019 QAEco Diversity and Inclusion Group Committee Member

2017 QAEco mentoring scheme Organiser

2015 - 2016 Staff-Student Consultative Committee, University of Freiburg Student Rep

Volunteering

2020 - present Start with a Friend e.V. Refugee support

2019 Orygen Youth Health International Student Welfare Project Peer leader

Societies

British Ecological Society, Australian Ecological Society, BUND (Friends of the Earth Germany)

Referees

Prof Brendan Wintle

MSc and PhD supervisor

Director NESP Threatened Species Recovery Hub University of Melbourne and University of Queensland b.wintle@unimelb.edu.au Dr Nick Golding

PhD Supervisor Research Fellow QAEco University of Melbourne

nick.golding.research@gmail.com